the Assumption in this video is that
torine is a heart healthy molecule and
I'll touch on some of the clinical data
but I'll leave most of that heavy
lifting for Content that I'll link for
you also this will be a pretty technical
explanation of torin's effects on your
heart cells so remain at your own risk I
was curious exactly what happens to your
body when your body is exposed to torine
keep in mind as we age our torine levels
can drop and rather significantly as
seen in this influence science paper
that I covered a while back you can see
age on the horizontal axis and torine
levels on the vertical clearly as time
passes blood torine levels drop to less
than half of that as a kid now of course
that's a simple Association but there's
plenty of clinical data also implicating
torine in having health benefits
including the heart through the
reduction of blood pressure in one
analysis that we covered previously
torine supplementation reduce blood
pressure in people with metabolic
syndrome as just one example but how
does it provide all these benefits to
the heart well according to this
analysis the blood pressure lowering
effects are explained by multiple
fascinating mechanisms but we can start
as torine is antagonistic role against a
hormone called Angiotensin 2 Angiotensin
2 is a molecule produced when its
precursor molecule Angiotensin one is
converted at your your lungs to
Angiotensin 2 once converted Angiotensin
2 can bind cells within your blood
vessels specifically your smooth muscle
cells and activate them to contract
since these cells surround the blood
vessel and are responsible for the
constriction of the vessel they increase
blood pressure when Contracting on a
mass scale I won't go into all the
cellular signaling that has to happen
but beyond the direct effect on smooth
muscle cells Angiotensin 2 also binds
endothelial cells these cells sit on the
very inner part touching the blood
coursing through your blood vessels
endothelial cells can also release
molecules that activate smooth muscle
cells to contract like a molecule known
as endothelin one in fact this study
shows that with increasing endothelin 1
exposed to the major blood vessels here
endothelin 1 increases constriction of
the blood vessel especially when tensin
2 is present in the black bars there the
researchers are simply increasing the
endothelin one concentration on the
horizontal axis there so Angiotensin 2
and endothelin 1 have a synergistic
effect the reason is because Angiotensin
2 not only directly activates the smooth
muscle cells to contract but it signals
the cells to generate more endothelin
one receptor as seen here note that the
black bars are a type of endothelin one
receptor and if more of the receptors
present that likely means that there's
greater signaling into the cell as you
can see the Angiotensin 2 addition
encourages the cells to generate many
times more endothelin one receptor
anyway torine plays a role when
combating Angiotensin 2 it does that
according to this review through a
unique mechanism you know how I said
that Angiotensin 2 activates your smooth
muscle cells in your blood vessels to
contract
well I also said I wasn't going to get
into the weeds of the mechanism well one
thing that you should know is that it's
generally calcium dependent so as
calcium in the cell Rises the cell
contracts there's way more between those
points but it's too much to cover now
toine does something unique in that the
toine transporter found in the cell
membrane of the smooth muscle cell is
what's known as a sorter so as toring
enters into the cell from the
bloodstream sodium comes along for the
ride as well so when sodium in the cell
Rises it's kicked back out by a
different transporter called a calcium
antiporter which means that sodium gets
ejected and calcium enters the cell that
keeps sodium down as the cell fills with
torine but it also fills with calcium I
hope you can see where I'm going with
this considering what I said about calci
increasing vessel constriction and
increasing blood pressure obviously this
goes against torin's blood pressure
lowering roll but that's where things
get weird let me show you a piece of
data here this is a measure of the
calcium levels in the cell if the bars
go up that means there's more calcium
notice that there are two conditions
control no torine added and the torine
added condition also notice that there's
a short exposure and a long exposure
you'll note that in the torine exposure
cellular calcium Rises as we just
detailed at least in the short exposure
long-term exposure leads to a mark drop
in calcium which would inactivate the
cell the exact reason for this change
over time is not fully understood but
one possibility is that the calcium is
pumped back out or diffuses out
similarly to how it enters which is
pretty darn cool at least I think in
short torine over time would reduce cell
activating calcium levels even as
Angiotensin 2 binds to the cell to
increase calcium levels which I think is
so freaking cool okay I'm going to be
covering another mechanism on an odd
hormonal system surrounding the liver in
the extended version of this video If
you're not all scienced out it'll be
included for the physionic Insiders
along with all of my work including
product recommend ations dosing
protocols and much more I'd love to have
you aboard the link is in the
description but let's cover another way
that toring reduces blood pressure a
hormone called epinephrine if we turn to
this review the researchers point out
that toring supplementation in humans
reduces epinephrine especially in people
with high blood pressure we see that
evidenced in one study they cite wherein
people were given torine and had their
epinephrine levels tested we see that
here so we're seeing measured blood
epidrin levels over time the white dot
on the top is hypertens of individuals
and the black dot and line are in the
middle is the hypertensive or high blood
pressure individuals using torine
there's clearly a significant drop in
epinephrine in full disclosure this is a
specialized scenario designed by the
researchers but this trend also has been
seen in other studies okay so why does
epinephrine matter
well when it's released from your
adrenal glands it can binded two nerve
cells throughout your body encouraging
them to release another molecule called
nor epinephrine this norepinephrine can
bind to the very same smooth muscle
cells that we discussed in the last
mechanism and guess what activate those
muscles to contract via the release of
calcium into the cell so the mechanism
by which that all occurs is slightly
different since the calcium release
comes from a compartment inside the
smooth muscle cell but let's not get
stuck on the details he said as the
entire video is swimming in details in
addition epinephrine is also believed to
bind smooth muscle cells and cause
similar
reactions if your eyes are crossed from
all the biology I don't blame you so the
takeaway here is well it's not really
applicable since we're discussing
mechanisms we need to use clinical data
for applic
but considering torin's clinical data
does indicate a blood pressure lowering
effect and we now know a few of the
mechanisms by which it does that you may
want to consider touring if you have
high blood pressure of note the effect
isn't huge but it does seem to be pretty
consistent but beyond blood pressure how
else can touring help we'll check out
these videos I'll see you over there
oh
[Music]